어지러운 전국 시대.
It is the turbulent Sengoku period.
카라쿠리인이 사는 지팡구국에서는 군웅할거하여 밤낮으로 접전이 계속되고
Warlords keep on fighting day and night over
Jipangu State, where Karakuri people live.
카라쿠리 무예가들도 승리와 영광을 꿈꾸며 맹렬히 싸우고 있었다.
Karakuri Martial Artists were sharpening their swords, dreaming of victory and honor.
그리고 지금, 카라쿠리 무예자 제일을 꿈꾸는 터무니없는 영웅이 탄생했다!
And now, a wild hero has arrived, seeking to be the number one Karakuri Martial Artist!
무사시 등장이오!
Musashi enters-dasu!
카라쿠리 검호전: 무사시 로드
Karakuri Kengouden
Musashi Road
(The Story of Karakuri Martial Artist: Road of Musashi)
사내는 언제나 세계 한가운데서
A man always dreams of the day
제일 강해질 날을
in the center of the world to become
아! 아! 꿈꿔라
AH! AH! the strongest
마음의 칼을 넓은 하늘로 번쩍 쳐들어
Raise the sword of your heart high to the wide sky
모험의 길의 막을 연다
Raise the curtain to the road of adventure
지팡구국을 떠도는 검호
A skilled swordsman roams on Jipangu State
그 이름은 카라쿠리인 무사시
His name is Musashi, a Karakuri man
격렬한 승부의 소리는
The sound of fierce duels
눈부신 인생
makes a life dazzle
싸웠던 어제보다도 오늘 강해진다
Battles of yesterdays make you stronger today
무예! 이도류 무사시
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
내일은 빛난다
Tomorrow will be glorious
격렬한 승부의 소리는
The sound of fierce duels
눈부신 인생
makes a life dazzle
싸우는 한껏 고요함과 함께
Fight the utmost with the stillness
무예! 이도류 무사시
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
미간이 반짝였다 무사시!!
His eyes shined! Musashi!!
산속의 미야모토 마을에서 목검을 쳐들고 난폭하게 굴던 무사시는
Once being rough in the Miyamoto village in mountains, Musashi was punished
타쿠안에게 처벌받게 되었지만 오츠루에게 구해져 수련의 길에 나섰다.
by Takuan, but Otsuru rescued him and Musashi went to train himself.
그리고 평생의 라이벌이 될 코지로하고 만났지만
He met Kojirō who will become his rival of life,
무참히 완패하고 만 무사시.
and he was completely defeated without mercy.
그의 앞길에는 먹구름이 닥친 것이었다.
Dark clouds were in front of him.
눈물의 수행은 배가 고프오
Training in Tears
Makes Me Hungry
이곳은 오카야마 성의 조우카 마을이다.
This place is Jouka village in Okayama castle.
이야기는 들었지만 조우카 마을이 이렇게 활기찰 줄은 몰랐소!
I've heard about this place, but I never thought this place would be so lively-dasu!
이렇게 아름다운 기모노가 있다니, 오츠루 씨에게 입혀보고 싶소!
To know that beautiful kimono exists, I want to see Otsuru wearing one-dasu!
오츠루 씨!
Otsuru!
시골뜨기 무사시에게 이곳의 모든 것은 놀랄 만한 것이었다.
Everything here surprised Musashi, a boor.
마츠카시의 석류 아니오!
Aren't these pomegranates from Matsukasi-dasu!?
2문.
2 mons.
돈을 내!
Pay the price!
돈?
Price?
설마 모른다고는 안 하겠지?
I hope you wouldn't say you don't know?
돈 정도는 알고 있소.
I know what a price is-dasu.
그럼 돈을 내!
Then pay the price!
왜오!
Why would I-dasu?
이건 파는 것이야! 그걸 먹었으면 돈을 내는 게 당연하지!
This is for sale! It is obvious that you have to pay!
뭐가 웃기냐!
What's so funny?!
이런 석류, 내 미야모토 마을에는 어디에든 있고 무료라오!
There are pomegranates everywhere in my Miyamoto village, and thus are free-dasu!
돈을 낸다면 그것이야말로 웃긴 일 아니오!
Paying for such thing is something to laugh about-dasu!
안타깝게도 여긴 미야모토 마을이 아니다! 자, 돈을 내라! 안 내면...
Too bad for ya, but you are not at Miyamoto village! Now, give me the money or...
도둑이다!
Thief!
뭐? 어디냐, 도둑!
What?! Where are you, thief?!
너 말이야!
I'm talking about you!
나?
Me?
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 될 이 무사시에게 도둑이라고 부르는 건 무슨 소리오!
What do you mean, to call this Musashi who will be the number one Martial Artist in Jipangu a thief-dasu?!
살려주세요!
Help me!
저건 분명히 여자아이의 비명!
That voice must be a scream from a girl!
이곳에서 한시라도 지체한다면 사내의 자격이 없소!
It is not manly to not go rescue her right now-dasu!
아저씨! 참수를 면했다니 운이 좋소!
Mister! Consider yourself lucky to be alive-dasu!
다행이네...
That's a relief...
아! 돈!
Hey! You still gotta pay!
여러 명의 무예가에게 둘러싸여 있던 건 니시다 히카루라는 여자아이였다.
The one surrounded by Martial Artists was a girl named Nishida Hikaru.
누나, 차 안 마실래?
Miss, would you like to have a tea?
한잔 하는건 어때?
Have a glass.
이 몸의 마차로 드라이브는 어때?
How about a drive on my wagon?
그만해 주세요!
Please stop!
누나!
Sis!
누, 누구냐!
Who was that?!
뭐야?
What the?
뭐, 뭐냐, 네놈은!
Who are you?!
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 될!
The future number one Martial Artist of Jipangu!
미야모토 마을의
From Miyamaoto village,
무사시라고 하오!
I am Musashi-dasu!
이 녀석!
Aren't you interesting?
다쳐도 모른다!
You might get hurt!
다치는 건 그쪽이오!
You're going to be hurt-dasu!
감사하오! 감사하오! 정말 고맙소!
Thanks! Thank you! Thank you so much!
그 무예가들은 요시오카 도장의 사람들입니다.
Those Martial Artists are from Yoshioka Dōjō.
요시오카 도장?
Yoshioka Dōjō?
네. 미야코에 있는 지팡구에서 제일 강한 무예가들이 모인 도장입니다.
Yes. It's a Dōjō in Miyako that the most powerful Martial Artists of Jipangu are at.
지팡구에서 제일 강하다고 하셨소?
Most powerful of Jipangu-dasu?
그 지부가 최근 이 조우카 마을에 생겼답니다. 요시오카 도장 소속이라 말만 하는 것으로 모두가 벌벌 떨 뿐이니...
Its branch has opened recently at here, Jouka.
Everyone tremble all over only by saying that one's a member of Yoshioka Dōjō...
뭐든 제 것인 양 행동하고...
They act as if everything is theirs.
그래도 이 무사시가 있는 한 더 이상 무서워 할 필요 없소!
But as long as Musashi's here, no need to fear-dasu!
그래도 조심해요. 아까는 초보들 뿐. 더 강한 자들이 가득 있답니다!
Don't let your guards down. Your opponent were mere beginners; there are lots of strong people!
에이, 괜찮소! 지금까지 나, 단 한번밖에 진 적이 없소!
No need to worry! Until now, I only lost a battle once-dasu!
무사시 씨라면 정말 믿고 맡겨도 될 것 같은 분이네요!
I think I really can trust upon you, Musashi!
자, 드세요! 아지지만의 단고에요.
You can eat this! They are dangos exclusively from Ajijiman.
우와, 맛있어 보이는 단고오!
Whoa, these dangos really look tasty-dasu!
잘 먹겠소!
Thank you for the meal!
그 요리!
That dish!
과연 살아서 먹을 수 있을까.
Will you be able to eat it alive?
세쥬로
Seijuro
어이, 거기. 뭐라고 말 좀 해봐라.
Hey, you. Say something.
알고 싶으면 먼저 이름을 대시오.
Tell me your name first if you want to know-dasu.
뭐라고?!
What did you say?!
난 요시오카. 요시오카 세쥬로!
I am Yoshioka. Yoshioka Seijuro!
요시오카 세쥬로!
Yoshioka Seijuro!
수도에서 오신 요시오카 가문의 대선생의 자제분으로 우리들의 스승이시다!
He is our master who is a son of the master of Yoshioka Family from the capital!
여기 오카야마에 요시오카 도장 지부 문을 열고 난 이후 처음으로 특별히 왕림하신 것이다!
It's the first time he came to specially visit someone by himself ever since he opened Yoshioka Dōjō at here, Okayama!
난 미야모토 마을의 무사시라고 하오.
I am Musashi from Miyamoto village-dasu.
그래서 용건이 무엇이오?
So what's your business-dasu?
우리 젊은이가 불쌍하게 당했다고 하서 그 예를 다하러 왔다.
I heard that our young students were attacked, so I came to repay you.
예? 음... 나 말이오?
Huh? That's a honor.
그래서 뭘 주실 거오?
So what's your payment-dasu?
만두?
Manju?
물양갱?
Red bean paste?
카스텔라?
Sponge cake?
이거다!
This!
목검이...
My wooden sword...
이자식!
You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay! You! Pay!
칼등이다.
Back side of sword.
역시 세쥬로 님!
That's our master Seijuro!
무사시!
Musashi!
흥. 입만 큰 녀석.
Hmph. He wasted my time with his mouth.
그러나 이런 자는 살려둘 방법이 없군.
Thus there is no way to let him live.
세상을 위해서는 이런 자는 빨리 사라지는 게 낫다.
A man like this should disappear for the world as soon as possible.
각오해라!
Be prepared!
시원하다!
How refreshing!
네이놈, 어디서 감히!
How dare you!
보쿠덴
Bokuden
이런, 어린이를 상대로 어른들이 열이 뻗치셨구만.
Ho ho ho. I see you adults are angry about a young kid.
이게... 네놈부터 쓰러트려주마! 내려와라!
How dare... You're going down first! Get down here!
위험해!
Look out!
뭐, 뭐야?!
Wha... what the?!
젠장!
Damn!
어떻냐, 칼을 빼려는 순간! 너는 이 몸에게 한 방이란다.
How's that? By taking your sword out, I easily determined your ability at once.
(무토도리: 無刀取り. 자신은 칼을 들지 않고 칼을 든 상대를 이김)
무토도리!
(Mutodori: 無刀取り. Defeating opponent with sword without using one)
Mutodori!
너도 잠깐 여기서 자고 있어라.
You should take a short nap too.
졸린 참에 가볍게 운동을 했군.
That was a nice stretch to wake me up.
이것 참, 고맙구만.
Thank you for the service.
자, 잠깐 기다리시오. 이런 대단한 무예가가 이런 곳에 있을 줄은...
Wait for a moment. I didn't thought such excellent Martial Artist would be here...
무슨, 단지 늙은이일 뿐이다.
Nah, I'm just a plain old guy.
하다못해 존함이라도...
Name, at least...
보쿠덴이다.
Bokuden.
켄세토에게 당했다던 츠카하라 보쿠덴!
Tsukahara Bokuden! You were told to be defeated by Kenseitou!
실례했습니다!
I sincerely apologize!
저 사람이 츠카하라 보쿠덴! 허점 가득해 보였는데 어디에도 허점이 없어!
That guy is Tsukahara Bokuden! He looked like he was full of weak points, and yet he has none at all!
보쿠덴...
Bokuden...
무사시 님, 상처는?
Mr. Musashi, are you hurt?
무사시 님!
Mr. Musashi!
보쿠덴을 따라가 어디에 갈 것이냐, 무사시! 질풍노도의 후반을 기다려라!
Where do you think you're going by following Bokuden, Musashi? Wait for the stormy latter half!
카라쿠리 검호전 무사시 로드
Karakuri Kengouden: Musashi Road
by Subdivers
기다려 주시오!
Please wait!
거기! 기다리라는 말이 안 들리시오!
Hey there! Can't you hear me asking you to stop-dasu?
그래!
Right!
돈을 떨어뜨렸소!
You've dropped your money!
어, 뭐?
Wait, what?
절 제자로 받아들여 주시오!
Please accept me as your pupil-dasu!
떨어뜨린 돈을 돌려주는 대신 제자로 삼아 달라니 말도 안 된다.
You're asking me to have you as a pupil in exchange for the money I dropped? Nonsense.
뭐라?
What?
멈춰라, 바보쿠덴!
Stop! Bakaden!
이 녀석! 난 보쿠덴이다!
Hey, now! I am Bokuden!
날 제자로 해라!
Take me as your pupil!
난 제자 키우는 취미는 없다.
Raising pupil isn't my hobby.
난 제자 되는 것이 취미이오!
My hobby is to be a pupil-dasu!
날... 제자로...
Make... me... your... pupil...
보쿠덴을 따라 삼천리,
Following Bokuden for 10,000 kilometers...
까진 아니어도, 무사시는 끈질기게 따라갔다.
...well, not that much, but anyway, Musashi stubbornly kept following.
해냈다...
I did it...
부탁이오!
Please!
깊이 마음먹고 목숨을 거는 것, 이것이 무사시의 방법이오!
Hardening and risking myself are the way of Musashi-dasu!
어이! 왜 그러냐! 정신 차려라!
Hey! What's wrong? Wake up!
한 그릇 더!
Another dish!
부탁이오!
Please-dasu!
그렇게까지 굴면 어쩔 수 없지. 제자로 해 주겠다.
You're too impolite to reject, so what can I do? You're my pupil from now on.
그 대신! 수련은 쓰라릴 것이다.
But! The training will be painful!
쓰라리니까 수련이잖소?
Aren't all trainings painful-dasu?
어? 뭐, 그렇지.
Huh? Well, I guess.
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되기 위해서라면 불 속이든 물 속이든 어디든 어떤 쓰라린 수련이라도 받아 보이겠소!
To become the number one Martial Artist of Jipangu,
I'll do my best for any training no matter how painful it is - in water or in fire-dasu!
알겠소? 어떤 어려운 상대라도 구름 머얼리... 날려 주겠소.
Got it? No matter what kind of opponent is, I'll hit him hard and make him fly... over the cloud-dasu.
참 이상한 녀석이군.
What a strange guy.
무사시! 츠카하라 보쿠덴의 제자가 되었냐!
Musashi! You managed to become the pupil of Tsukahara Bokuden?
네 녀석은 좋은 라이벌이 될 지도 모르겠군.
You might become my good rival after all.
허리에 힘이 없다! 허리에!
Keep your waist straight!
검을 다룰 때 제일 중요한 것은 허리에 힘을 주는 것이다!
The most important step of using a sword is keeping your waist straight!
네!
Got it!
알겠느냐, 무사시?
Do you understand, Musashi?
단련
Body
Training
담련
Mental
Training
단련은 단련!
You will train your body!
담련은 즉 담력.
You will raise guts by mental training.
담력은 어떤 일이 있어도 당황하지 않는 강한 정신력을 말한다.
Gut means the spiritual strength of not getting perplexed no matter what happens.
그 담력을 훈련하기 위해서는 자연과 기술을 단련하는 것이다.
To raise your guts, you must understand the nature and train your skills.
네!
Got it!
상대에게 이기기 위해서는 발도 빨라지지 않으면 안 된다!
To defeat an opponent, your feet must be as quick as your sword!
가끔은 달아나는 게 이기는 것일 때도 있다!
Sometimes to run away is to win!
네!
Got it!
몸도 당연 강해지지 않으면 안 된다.
Of course your body also has to become strong.
네!
Got it!
10년은 이르군.
Ten years early, I see.
알았냐, 무사시. 현실 수련에서 가장 중요한 것은
Do you understand, Musashi? The most essential elements of real-life training are
1. 눈 (일안), 2. 발 (이족), 3. 배짱 (삼담), 4. 힘 (사력)이다.
Vision (eye) first, pace (foot) second, audacity third, and force fourth.
이 힘과 담력과 속도는 이미 배웠지.
You've already learned the force, audacity, and the pace.
이 "안"이라는 것은 보는 걸 말한다. 한마디로 말하자면 상대를 보는 것.
Vision means to see. To be exact, it means to see your opponent.
여기에는 "안"의 눈과 "검"의 눈이라는 게 있다.
There are two kinds of Vision: Vision of eye, and Vision of sword.
"안"의 눈은 직감, "검"의 눈은 사물의 현상을 보는 것이다.
Vision of eye means intuition; Vision of sword means to observe the phenomenon of objects.
이 녀석아, 내가 기껏 먹을 시간까지 아껴가며 가르쳐주고 있는데...
I'm teaching you even using my dinner time and you're...
내 밥까지 먹었구나...
You even ate my dinner!
해, 해냈다!
I did it!
휼륭하다, 무사시. 오늘부터는 제 2단계로 나아가겠다.
Good job, Musashi. From today we will go to the second step.
네!
Thank you!
왜 그러냐, 오츠루.
What's the problem, Otsuru?
아, 스님... 저, 사과해야만 하는 것이...
Master... I have something I must apologize.
무사시를 달아나게 둔 것 말이냐?
About letting Musashi run away?
네.
Yes.
아니다, 잘 말해 주었다, 오츠루.
Don't worry. You did a good job, Otsuru.
사실 슬슬 놔주어도 될 것이라고 생각하던 참이었다.
I was thinking that it was time to let him go anyway.
그러나 내가 용서해 자유가 된 것보다도 너의 녀석을 소중히 여기는 마음을 접고 엄하게 대할 필요도 있단다.
I forgave him for now, but as I did, sometimes you just have to stop thinking much of him and be harsh to him.
뭐든 무사시를 위해서 잘 될 테다!
Everything will turn out to be well for Musashi!
무사시 녀석, 지금쯤 어디서 뭘 하고 있으려나.
I wonder what's Musashi doing at where.
뭐, 그래도 어떻게든 걱정할 필요는 없다!
But no need to worry at all!
무사시니까. 씩씩하게 뭐든 해낼 테니까!
He's Musashi after all. He'll bravely fight for his future.
무디다! 무뎌!
Soft and naive!
스승님!
Master!
뭔 짓이오!
What are you doing-dasu?!
바보 녀석! 실제 싸움에서 구해주는 놈이 있을 거라 생각하나!
You idiot! Do you think your opponent is going to save you in the real battle?
무사시 씨!
Musashi!
무사시 씨! 정신 차려요! 이런 곳에서 죽어도 괜찮아요?
Musashi! Get a grip! Do you think it is fine to die in such place?
오츠루 씨.
Otsuru.
무사시! 이런 곳에서 뻗다니 말할 가치도 없는 놈이구나!
Musashi! If you drop dead in such place, you don't even worth being discussed about!
바보 녀석.
Idiot.
코지로!
Kojirō!
괜찮은 녀석이었다... 죽을 때까지 검을 놓지 않다니.
He was a fine guy... I'm surprised that he's still holding his sword after death.
빈틈이오!
Chink in the armor!
잘 했다, 무사시.
Good job, Musashi.
실례했습니다!
Excuse me!
무사시, 너도 하산할 때가 온 듯 하구나.
Musashi, it's time for you to leave.
시대의 풍운이 날 부른다.
Winds of era is calling me.
무사시! 넌 미야코에 가라!
Musashi! You shall go to Miyako!
미야코에?
To Miyako?
너에게는 더 이상 알려줄 게 없다. 내가 가진 모든 것을 알려준 셈이다.
I do have nothing more to teach. It's like I taught everything I know to you.
나머지는 무사시, 네가 네 손으로 직접 발전시켜 나가거라.
For the rest, Musashi, you shall develop yourself with your hands!
할 수 있겠나, 무사시?
Can you do so, Musashi?
네!
Yes!
무사시! 우선 지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되어라!
Musashi! First, become the number one Martial Artist in Jipangu!
감사합니다!
Thank you!
마지막으로 검의 궁극의 목적은 단 하나!
Lastly, do not forget the ultimate purpose of a sword!
싸우지 않고 이기는 것.
To win without fighting.
가라, 무사시! 미래의 지팡구를 위해서!
Go, Musashi! For the future of Jipangu!
네!
Got it!
이 이상 무리하면 견딜 수가 없겠군.
It will be a problem if I get tired over my limits.
그래도 녀석, 꽤 근성있고 재미있는 녀석이었어.
Still, he was an interesting guy with a good gut.
청운의 뜻을 품고 미야코에! 미야코에! 그 무사시의 앞길을 기다리는 것은 꽃인가, 폭풍인가!
To Miyako with a high ambition! Go, Musashi! What will be waiting for him? A flower, or a storm?
그러나! 무사시여, 가라! 꽃에도 폭풍에도 뛰어들어라! 그것이야말로 검을 잡은 사내의 길.
That does not matter! Go forward, Musashi! Dive into flowers and storms! That's the road of a man with a sword.
허공의 주머니에 달이
Sometimes the moon jumps over
뛰어넘어가는 일도 있어
the pocket of the empty sky
큰 소리로 웃으면
Laugh loudly and
내일에는 아침이 와
a morning will come tomorrow
잃는 것 따위는 아무것도 아니야
Don't care too much about losing
계속 해나가! 앞으로 가!
Keep doing! Go for it!
맨손은 강해
A bare hand is strong
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
인생 그런 거야! 기회가 어라,
That's how life is! Look, a chance
꼬리를 흔들며 쫒아와!
follows us wagging its tail!
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
미래도 그런 거야! 내일이 어라,
That's how future also is! Look, tomorrow
양손을 벌리고 웃고 있어!
is opening its hands and smiling at us!
혹독한 수련 후에, 한층 강해진 나는 미야코 궁전을 향하오.
After a severe training, I became stronger and now I'm heading for Miyako palace-dasu.
이야, 역시나 대도시, 이상한 녀석이 많소!
Wow, it sure is a big city, and there sure are lots of weird guys-dasu!
칼을 천 개 모으는 것이 취미라는 거대한 괴승 앞에 나타난 것은, 어린아이 같은 용모의 누군가.
In front of a giant fighter whose hobby is collecting thousands swords, some child-looking guy appears.
다음 이야기! 수도의 고조의 벤케이오
Next story! Benkei from Gojo in the Capital
네 눈동자를 뚫고 갈 것이오!
It will pierce through your eyes-dasu!
다음 이야기
수도의 고조의 벤케이오
재미있게 보세요!
Next Story
Benkei from Gojo in the Capital
We hope you enjoy!